Subtitles by dhyco
好吧，好吧，这样就行
Hey, okay ... now...
我们再做一次
let's go again.
哪个在做实验？九号吗？
Which one's this, number9? - Yeah, number 9.  Bright eyes.
对，这是九号
美瞳，我们这么称呼她的
你在看吗？
Are you watching this?
这真是不可置信
This, this is unbelieveable.
哦，我的天
Oh, my God.
一那有多少步？ 一20
How many moves was that? - 20.
对，完美的分数是15
The perfect score is 15. God, what, what are you giving her?
博士，你给了她什么？
嘿，给我那个视频！
Hey, give me that video!
黑猩猩九号，只打了一剂
Chimp number 9, just one dose.
稍后我会见到你么？
Couldn't I see you later? - We're good to go.
我们准备好演示了
我会给你回电话 对，好的，谢谢，再见
I'm going to call you back. Yeah, all right.  Thanks, Bye.
112是有效的
112, it works.
只试过一只猿而已
On just the one primate? - One is all we need.
一只就足够了 完全的认知恢复，我们准备好了
Full cognitive recovery.
你确定你没有太赶吗？
We're ready.
Look, are you sure you're not rushing this?
我已经花了五年半时间了
I've been working on this for five and a half years.
数据很清楚
The data is clear. We're ready, Steven.
我们准备好了，史蒂芬
我唯一需要的就是你关于人类试验的批准
All I need is your approval for human trials.
关于这个你需要得到董事会的批准
Oh, for this, you're going to need the Board's approval.
有大量的金钱栽在这上面，威尔
There's a lot of money riding on this, Will.
你只有一个机会
You only get one shot. - One shot is all I need.
一个机会对我而言就够了
[sighs]
好吧，但是我要看看
All right. I'll need to see all the research.
一所有的研究 一那是当然的
You got it!
一还有，威尔… 一什么事儿？
Oh, and Will ... - Yeah?
把你自身的情感置之度外
Keep your personal emotions out of it.
这些人投资的是结果，不是梦想
These people invest in results, not dreams.
好
Okay!
来见见黑猩猩九号
Meet chimp 9. Here she's tasking at what is called the Lucas Tower.
这里她在完成叫卢卡斯塔的一项任务
目的是把塔一个一个桩地移开
The object of which is to move the tower from peg to peg
不能把大的积木放在小积木上
without placing a larger block on top of a smaller block.
如我所料，她根本无法完成这个谜题游戏
As expected, she was unable to complete the puzzle at all.
然后，我们给了她我们称为ALZ一1 12的东西
Then, we gave her what we call, ALZ-112, a gene therapy
这是一种基因疗程 允许大脑创建自己的细胞
that allows the brain to create its own cells in order to repair itself.
来修复自身
生物学上，这叫神经形成 这里在基希斯
In biology, this is called neurogenesis.
Here, at GEN-SYS,
我们把它称为阿尔茨海默病克星
we call it a cure to Alzheimer's.
东尼，你帮她准备好了么？
Donnie, you get her ready? - She's got stage fright.
她怯场了
是这样的吗？
Is that what it is?
嘿！嘿！
Hey, ape.
她要弄断我的手了！
She's gonna break my arm!
放手，美瞳，放手！
Bright Eyes! Let go!
你还好吗？
Are you all right?
我们准备继续到下一阶段 人类试验
We're ready to move on to the next phase.
Human trials.
来吧，美瞳 这是你最爱的泡沫苏打水，来
Here you go, Bright Eyes. It's your favorite fizzy soda.
我们走吧，东尼 我们应该把她带到楼下了
Come on, let's go, Donnie.
好吗？好姑娘
We should have her downstairs already.
Okay. Good girl!
来吧，姑娘，那就对了
Come on out, girl, that's right.
这是给你的
That's for you.
套脖子上，东尼！套脖子上
Got her!
套脖子上！老天！
Jesus!
东尼，现在！打开！
Donnie, open the cage! Open up! Open up!
东尼！
我要给她打镇静剂
Going to sedate her!
一不不不！ 一门！关门！美瞳！
No, no! - Get the door!
不不不不
No, no! Hold it! Now!
关上，现在就关上！
去找人帮忙，东尼！东尼！快点
Call help! Donnie, Donnie!
112完全没有副作用
There have been absolutely no side effects associated
只有一个例外
with 112, with one exception.
不知道什么原因 黑猩猩的瞳孔有一些绿色的斑点
For some reason,
the chimps irises exhibit flecks of green.
其实，我们先在黑猩猩九号身上注意到
Actually, we first noticed it in chimp 9,
所有她才有这样的名字，美瞳 我们带她进来的时候你们会看到
hence her nickname, Bright Eyes.
You'll see when we bring her in.
，卜心！
Move!
理论上讲
In theory, this therapy can be used
这个疗程可以用于 大量脑科病症的治疗
to treat a wide range of brain disorders.
用途可以说是无限的
It's virtually limitless.
因此潜在的收益也是 这就是为什么
As are the potential profits.
我们很有信心 你们会投票批准人类的试验
which is why we are confident that
you will vote to approve human trials.
不！不！
No, no, no!
雅各布斯先生？雅各布斯先生，我求你了
Mr. Jacobs, Mr. Jacobs I am begging you,
我求你不要这么做
I am begging you, not to do this.
这会花相当一笔钱
Look, it costs a small fortune to
在所有这些黑猩猩身上操作实验
run lab workups on all of those chimps
只是会告诉我我已经知道的东西
only to tell me what I already know,
那就是它们有传染性
that they are contaminated.
有死亡的危险
There are lives at stake here.
这些动物有个性的 有依恋
These, these are animals with personalities,
with attachments.
一依恋？ 一对
Attachments? - Yeah.
我做的是生意，不是开宠物动物园的
I run a a business, not a petting zoo.
找一个最省钱最有效的方式 让这些猿类安乐死好了
Find the most cost effective way to put those apes down.
一我没法那么做 一你是黑猩猩饲养员，自己想办法
I can't do that.
You're the chimp handler.
Handle it.
史蒂芬？
Steven!
一那太好笑了 一他们拿走了112
Well, that was fun!
董事会拒绝了你的提案
They've taken the 112.
他们选择了推行其他的项目
Board has rejected your proposal.
They've chosen to advance other programs.
呢，一定有你可以做的事情
Well, there must be something that you can do.
对，肯定有的，我可以开除你
Yes. There is, I could fire you.
相信我，我们谈过的
Believe me, we talked about it.
我们有五年的有结论的数据
We have five years of conclusive data.
随你的便，展示所有的数据吧
Parade all the data you want,
你绝对不会说服任何一个人 来投资一分钱
you will never convince anyone to invest another dime.
这种药有潜力来拯救生命
This drug has the potential to save lives!
更像是会让公司破产
Bankrupt this company, more like.
我发誓，关于人类的大脑 你知道一切
I swear, you know everything about the human brain
除了其工作的方式
except the way it works.
回到112的早期计划上
Go back to the drawing board on the 112.
从分子发展重新开始
Start again in molecular development.
在别人搞定之前 先有结果
Find a way to get there before someone else does.
然后把这些混乱清理干净
And, clean up this mess.
富兰克林？
Franklin!
他们怀孕真看不出来
It's very small. She must have been
当他们把她带进来的时候 她肯定已经怀上了
pregnant when we brought her in.
这就是为什么…
So that's why ...
美瞳
She wasn't being aggressive. She was just being protective.
她并不是具有攻击性 她只是想保护？
她以为我们要伤害她的宝宝
She thought we were going to hurt her baby.
到这里来
我自己来带他 不过我的小叔子在保安部工作
I would take it myself,
but my brother-in-law works for security. He'd rat me out in a seceond.
他一发现会马上报告我的
什么，你要我带它回家？ 我没法照顾一只猴子
What, you want me to take it home?
I can't take care of a monkey.
一他不是猴子，是猿 一富兰克林，我…
He's not a monkey! He's an ape. - Franklin ...
只是几天而已，直到我找到收容所 我就需要这么多了
You know, it's just for a couple days until
I find a sanctuary.  That's all I need.
富兰克林，不 这不是我的责任
Franklin, no!
Look, this isn't my responsibility.
这是公司的财产
This, this is company property.
好吧，我告诉你吧，博士
Okay ...
I tell you what, Doc.
雅各布斯让我给其他12只实行安乐死
Jacobs made me put down the other 12.
我不理了
I'm done.
和我搭档吧
Be my guest.
一嘿 一晦
Hey! - Oh, hi.
一你看起来累坏了 一就是
You look beat. - Yeah. How's he doing?
他怎么样了？
呢，时好时坏
Well, he has good days and bad days.
今天，不太好 不过他在引用莎士比亚
Today, not so good, although he
has been quoting Shakespeare.
你带了只宠物
Oh, you got a pet?
只是暂时来家里作客
Uh, it's just a temporary house guest.
好吧，也许对他很好
Well, maybe that'll be good for him.
一对 一晚安
Good night!
鉴赏证书授予给 查尔斯罗德曼先生
[discordant piano playing]
嘿，爸爸
Hi, Dad!
一爸爸？ 一威尔！
Dad?
晦，我没听到你进来
Will! I didn't hear you come in.
今天很重要，对吗？
Today's the day, right?
你以为我会忘记
You thought I'd forget?
今天你有很重要的考试，对吗？ 化学的？
You have a big test today, right?
Chemistry?
嘿，爸爸，你想看点东西么？
Hey, Dad ...
什么？
You want to see something? - What?
那是什么？他受伤了么？
What is that? Is he injured?
没有，我想那是胎记
No, I think that's a birthmark.
“但是对凯撒而言
"As for Caesar, kneel down, kneel down and wonder!"
“跪下，跪下，想想”
对，不要有太多依恋
Yeah, don't get too attached.
他是个可爱的小家伙，不是么？
He's a cute little guy, isn't he?
我的汽车钥匙在哪儿？
Where's my car keys?
一我的汽车钥匙！你把它们放哪儿了？ 一爸爸
My car keys, where'd you put 'em?
你不再开车了
Dad, ... you a, you don't drive anymore.
我知道
I know that.
来
Here ...
为什么你不喂他吃点东西？
Why don't you feed him. Can you do that?
一你可以喂吗？ 一当然可以
Of course, I can..
威尔，看看他
Will! ... Look at this!
他多大？一天？两天？
How old is he? Like, a day old? Two days old?
对
Yeah ...
恩，他很聪明，不是吗？
He's a smart one, isn't he?
你想给他起什么名字？
What are you going to name him?
我不知道
I do not know ...
三年后
Three years later
现在，凯撒显示了 高度智商的迹象
Right away, Caesar displayed signs of intelligence heightened intelligence,
因此我养了他，把我的工作带回了家
so I kept him.   And, brought my work home.
到18个月时
By 18 months, Caesar was signing up to 24 words.
凯撒可以打24个词的手语
到两岁时
By age two, Caesar completing puzzles and models
凯撒可以完成谜题游戏和模型
为八岁或者以上的孩子设计的游戏
designed for children eight years and up.
在三岁时
At age three,
凯撒继续显示出认知技巧
Caesar continues to show cognative skills
远远超过了同龄的人类
that far exceed that of his human counterpart.
回家，回家
Home ... home.
他只用三步就完成了卢卡斯塔
He completed the Lucas Tower in 15 moves, a perfect score.
完美得分
我坚持我的假设
I maintain my hypothesis that: A. The green in his eyes indicate
就是，A，他眼里的绿色 表明ALZ一112
that the ALZ-112 was passed genetically from mother to son
通过基因遗传从母亲传给了儿子
还有，B，在需要替代的损伤细胞缺失方面
and, B. That in the absence of damaged cells that need to be replacing
在他体内的药显著地 增加了健康大脑的功能
the drug in his system has radically boosted healthy brain functioning.
并且
And, ...
he plays chess pretty well.
他棋也玩得很好
那是我的灯！我的房间！
[shouting]
爸爸？
Dad!
一我这里不需要你 一爱丽拉，我很抱歉
I'm sorry. - I can't do this, anymore.
我不能再做了
他需要去养老院 没有别的办法让他生活
He belongs in a home.
This is no way for him to live.
对，没有别的办法
No way to live?
没有办法生活下去
现在，这是我的灯，我总是…
I broke my lamp ...
这会让你感觉好些，爸爸
It'll make you better, Dad.
[Shhh...]
爸爸？
Dad!
[exuberant piano playing]
托德！进来吃早饭！
Todd, come inside for breakfast.
我需要对我从实验室拿出的东西做个记录
I'll need to keep track of what I take from the lab,
不过，我觉得你不需要 一个月进行一次以上的治疗
although I don't see you needing more than one treatment a month.
一惊异的事情发生了 一是么
Something amazing has happened!
我需要血样测试 一个扫描和剂量
I'll need a blood test, a scan and the dosage ...
一你要小心地监察 一威尔…
carefully monitored.
现在如果我能偷一些…
Now, if I can sneak ...
一威尔！ 一什么？
Will!  I'm not sick, anymore!
我没病了
没什么的，爸爸
It was nothing, Dad.
凯撒，凯撒在哪儿？我想看看他
Ceasar.  Where's Caesar? I want to see him.
凯撒？
Caesar!
凯撒！
恩，他不会跑太远的
He can't have gone far.
凯撒！
Caesar!
爸爸？爸爸！
Daddy!
凯撒！
Caesar!
出去！出去！
Get out of here! Get out!
出去！离开这里！
Get out!
嘿嘿嘿！够了！够了！
Hey, hey, hey ... Enough! Enough!
你究竟是怎么了？
It doesn't matter what you do.
如果我再看到那只畜生 接近我家或者我的孩子…
If I catch that animal anywhere near my house or my kids, again ...
他没有危险的
He's not dangerous.
一不会再发生了 一好吧，不会的
It won't happen again.
Damn right, it won't!
来吧，爸爸
Come on, Dad. - He, he just wanted to play.
他只是想玩玩
呆在家里，爸爸搞定了
Stay in the house! Daddy's got you.
我告诉你了没有我们不要一个人出门
I told you not to go out without us.
哦，天啊，好吧
It's okay ...
有多糟糕？
How bad is it?
我不知道
I do not know.
他喜欢你
He likes you. - Uh, huh.
别担心
Don't worry. It'll be over soon.
很快就包扎完了，我们就去买个奖品
Then, we can go get a treat.
我想冰淇淋不错
I'm thinking, ice cream.
好主意
Good idea!
你教了他手语？
You taught him to sign?
只是一点点
Just, handful of things, basic stuff.
基础的东西
他在说什么？
What's he saying?
没什么
Nothing.
你认为我们什么时候应该回来？
So, when do you think we should come back?
哦，你不需要再回来 因为缝线会吸收的
Well, you won't need to come back.
because, um, the stiches are dissolveable.
我想说的只是 需要小心感染迹象
I would just say, watch for signs of infection.
发烧，发红
Fever ... redness ...
好，现在他说什么？
Okay, what's he saying, now?
Um,
恩，他认为你和我应该一起吃饭
well, ...
he thinks that you and I should have dinner together.
我知道
(chuckling) I ... know ...
嘿，凯撒，过来
Caesar! Come on!
真高兴又见到你，卡罗琳
Good to see you, again, Caroline.
你来吗，凯撒？
You coming, Caesar?
恩，你的秘密武器是什么？
So, what's your secret?
不算我的功劳，是他的基因
Oh, I can't take any credit. It's in his genes.
我想你真是太谦虚了 他真是让人惊异
I think you're being very modest.
He's pretty amazing.
我想你在这里为凯撒 创建了一个很棒的家
I think you've built a pretty good home for Caesar, here.
但是？
他不会一直都这样的
You know he won't stay this way for long.
很快他会长成一只 大型的有力的动物
He's going to soon grow into
a large, powerful, animal.
来这儿
Come here!
他的腿怎么样？
How's he been doing?
还好，我想
Okay, I think.
我喜欢黑猩猩，我也很怕他们
I love chimpanzees.
I'm also afraid of them.
怕他们是正常的
And, it's appropriate to be afraid of them.
凯撒不会伤害任何人
Caesar will never hurt anyone.
嘿！嘿！
他在这儿很开心，来吧
He's happy here.
对，我看得出来
Yeah, I see that.
我们至少给他点开放的空间吧？
We can at least give him some open space?
对，那可能是个好主意
- Yeah. That would prpbably be a good idea.
我知道桥之后有个地方 红木林，简直是天堂
I know a place right across the bridge,
the Redwoods.  It's a paradise.
来，来
Come on!
到这里来
Come here.
他不需要项圈的 他会乖乖的，来吧
Doesn't need a leash! He'll be fine. Come on!
只是安全起见，来吧
Just to be safe. - Come on, Caesar!
来吧，凯撒
谬尔国家森林公园
It's the redwoods.
这是红木林
凯撒？好吧
Caesar!
All right.
如果我把这个解下 你不能离开我的视野
If I take this off you can not leave my sight.
不然我再也找不到你了，好吧
I'll never find you again.
Okay.
一这是什么？ 一他在做什么？
What's this? - What's he doing?
我真不敢相信
I don't believe that! - What?
一什么？ 一他在请求你的允许
He's asking your permission.
是一个谦卑的手势
It's a supplicating gesture.
可以
It's okay.
来吧，凯撒，你可以开跑了！
Come on, Caesar! Off you go!
看他跑的
Look at him go!
一凯撒！ 一凯撒！
Caesar!
Caesar!! - Caesar!!
凯撒！
Caesar!
找到你了
There you are ...
凯撒？
Caesar!
继续，凯撒，爬吧！
Come on, Caesar, climb!
再高点
Go higher!
加油爬！
Climb!
，卜心点
Be careful!
凯撒，小心！
Caesar, be careful!
五年后
FIVE YEARS LATER
晦
Hi!
发生什么了，伙计？
What's going on, buddy?
也给你一些爱
Give some love.
过来，甜心
Come on, honey.
那是只黑猩猩吗？
Is that a chimpanzee?
晦
[dog snarls & barks]
别这样！
Come on!
来吧
[Caesar snarls back at dog]
[dog whimpers]
凯撒？凯撒
Caesar! ... Caesar!
来
Come on!
没事了，来吧
It's all right. Come on.
没事了，过来
Come on!
我们走吧，上车？
Let's go.
Are you getting in?
凯撒？
Caesar ...
你好么，伙计？
You okay, pal?
你是一只宠物吗？不是
Are you pet? ... No.
You're not a pet.
你不是一只宠物
我是你爸爸
I am your father.
凯撒是什么？
What is Caesar?
好吧
Okay ...
基希斯
凯撒，这是我工作的地方
Caesar, this is where I work.
这是你出生的地方
This is were you were born.
你妈妈曾在这里 和其他的黑猩猩一起
Your mother was here with other chimpanzees.
但是她现在不在这里了
But she's not here, anymore ...
因此
so ...
这就是为什么 我把你带回家和我一起住的原因
... that's why I took home to live with me.
对
Yeah.
你妈妈去世了
Your mother's dead.
原因是，她被施了药
The thing is, she was given medicine,
就像我给查尔斯的药一样
like the medicine I give to Charles.
她把药传给了你
She passed it on to you.
这就是为什么你很聪明
That's why you're so smart.
我们把他带回家吧
Let's take him home.
好的
来，给我解释一下
Come on, explain it to me.
好吧
All right.
我把他偷偷带出实验室 为了救他一命
I snuck him out of the lab to save his life.
我不知道那个药效 直接从他妈妈身上传到了他身上
I had no idea that the effects had been transfered vertically from his mother.
但从此之后 他一直显示出惊人的智商迹象
But, since then, he's been displaying incredible signs intelligence.
我把112设计为修复型 但是凯撒远远超越了这个界限
I designed the 112 to repair, but Caesar's gone way beyond that.
这是他去年的lQ
Here's his IQ from last year.
从那之后，已经翻倍了
Since then, it's doubled.
这不对劲，威尔
This is all wrong.
我父亲离去了 这个药把他救了回来
My father was on gone this drug brought him back.
你从没看到他有多么糟糕
You never saw how bad he was.
一他又一次拥有了生命 一凯撒怎么办？
He has his life again.
And, what about Caesar? - What about him?
一什么他怎么办？ 一他属于哪里？
How does he fit in?
和我一起
With me, ... with us ...
和我们一起
Listen, ...
听着
I know it has been hard for you,
我知道对你而言很难
但是你在尝试控制事态 而那本不该由你控制的
but you are trying to control things that were never meant to be controlled.
112是有效的
The 112 works.
Do you realize how you sound?
你意识到了你说话的语气么？
All I'm saying is this is a good thing.
我所说的就是，这是一件好事
凯撒就是最好的证明，我父亲也是
Caesar's proof of that.
So's my father.
凯撒，吃你的饭
Caesar, eat your food.
爸爸，你还好吗？
Dad, are you okay?
对，我还好
Yeah, I'm fine.
抗体
Antibodies.
他的系统找到了一种打击112病毒的方式
His system has found a way to fight the 112 virus
因此没法输送疗程
so that it can't deliver its therapy.
我父亲的病症会 加倍复发
My father's disease is going to return with a vengence.
甜心，你看到汽车蜡了么？
是木斯堂
看起来不错，我做的就是…
停下！
Stop!
现在给我停下！
Stop, right now!
嘿！嘿！
Hey! Get out there! Get out of that car!
离开那儿！给我从车里出来！
你他妈的在干啥？ 从我车里出来！
What the hell are you doing? Get out of my car!
我说，给我从车里出来！
I said, get out of my car!
我是飞行员！我得去机场！
I'm a pilot! I've got to get to the airport!
现在我怎么去，嗯？
How am I gonna get there now, huh?
你他妈给我答句话啊！ 你在干什么？
Answer the God-damn question! What were you doing?
我有辆车刚…
I have a car just exactly ...
恩，那显然不是…
I'm done ... the police can handle it.
就这样了，我说完了 警察会处理的
Stay right there! You aren't going nowhere, mister!
你就呆在那里！ 你哪儿也不能去，先生！
你或者你儿子得为这个付出代价！
You will pay!
但是我保证我他妈绝对不会！ 这是你的问题！你制造了混乱！
This is your problem, you make it happen!
一我烦死你们俩了！ 一我不会…
... not through with you! Stay right there!
你就呆在那里！
不！
不！不！
凯撒！停下！
Caesar, stop!
爸爸！
Daddy!
不不
凯撒！
Caesar!
好了
It's okay.
好了，你不是有意的
He didn't mean it.
没事了
It's okay ...
嘿，把那东西从他身上解开
Hey, hey, take that thing off of him!
你可以把那个从他身上解开吗？ 来吧
Take that thing off of him!
我会带他进去，好吗？
Look, I'll take him in, okay?
不，他现在属于法庭监管 你不能那么做
No, he's under court orders. We can't do that.
那可以的，让他那么做吧
It's fine! Let him.
你准备好了就带他进来
Bring him in when you're ready.
一把那个取下 一谢谢
Take it off.
Thank you!
凯撒，凯撒，凯撒，凯撒？凯撒
Caesar, Caesar, Caesar, ... Caesar, Caesar.
现在不要这样，会没事的
Not right now. It's going to be okay.
我们就看看里面有什么，好吗？
Let's just see what it's like inside, okay.
来吧凯撒，我们走
Come on, Caesar.
Let's go.
圣布鲁诺 灵长类收容所
来吧，相信我
Come on, ... trust me.
没事的
It's okay.
去吧
Go.
他没有和其他黑猩猩一起玩过
He hasn't spent any time with other chimps.
我们已经习惯了
Oh, we're used to that.
刚开始他会有点害羞怕怕 但是我们会让他融入的
He'll be a little skittish at first, but we'll integrate him.
你会很惊奇他们适应得那么快
You'd be surprised how quick they adapt.
我们提供一个激发性的环境
We provide a stimulating environment.
他在这里会进步很快的
He's going to thrive here.
来吧，我们有些文书要签
Come, let's do some paperwork.
你进来时确保锁上门
Make sure you lock that door when you come in.
凯撒
Caesar!
一切都会好的
You'll be okay!
Everything's going to be okay!
不要害怕
Don't be scared.
现在你要呆在这里
You're going to stay here, now.
不
No ... Not going home right now.
现在我们不回家
没事的
It's OK.
根据我们的经验而言 告别的时间越长
The longer you drag out the good-byes,
就越艰难
the harder it is.
我可以稍后签吗？
Can I sign that later?
你很可能会想念他 比他想念你更多
You'll probably miss him more than he'll miss you.
最好给他几周时间 来适应这个地方
You'd best give him a couple of weeks to get used too the place.
威尔，我们得走了
Will, we have to go.
我们得回家了
We have to go home.
我很快就会回来，好吗？
Coming back soon, okay?
在你回来前打个电话
Just call ahead, before you do.
嘿，过来！
Hey, over here!
嘿，我可以把你弄出去！
Hey, I can get you out!
来，过来
Come on!  Over here!
来，嘿，下来
Hey, down here.
傻冒的猴子
Stupid monkey ...
你就只能这么做吗？喂！ 这是个疯人院！
So you? Come on, make it!
这是个疯人院！
法院的传讯还没有送出 所以不在系统里
Court order hasn't been filed, so it's not in the system.
一旦通过了 会花大约90天
Once it comes through,
你才能收到上诉日期
it will take about 90 days before you receive an appeal date.
一90天？ 一对，先生，90天
90 days? - Yes, sir, 90 days.
一你会收到邮件通知 一等一下
You'll be notified by mail.
好吧，事情会这么发生 你会回到电脑前
Here's what's going to happen.
你最好把事情调整好
You're going to go back to your computer, you know, shift things around
这周你就得给我一个上诉的日期 你明白了么？
and you're going to get me a date for my appeal, this week, you got it?
我没法帮助你
I can't help you.
好吧，那我们问题就大了 因为除非你这么做，否则我不会离开的
All right, then we have a problem.
Because, I'm not moving until you do.
90天，先生
90 days, sir. Be thankful you're talking about court dates.
你有个法庭日期已经不错了，要感恩
你很幸运他们没有让所有的动物安乐死
You're lucky they didn't put that animal down.
我保证我会很快接他回来，爸爸
I promised to get him back soon, Dad.
爸爸？
Dad?
我父亲的免疫系统一直抵御112病毒
My father's immune system continues to reject the 112 virus,
让基因疗程完全无效
rendering the gene therapy obsolete.
他的健康日渐恶化 疾病蔓延很迅速
his health is deteriorating, and the disease is progressing rapidly.
我需要一个更具攻击力的病毒应变
I need a more aggressive virus strain,
更快速的传递方式
a faster delivery method,
因为以这个效率…
because at this rate ...
我不能同时失去他们两个
I can't lose them both.
我不会失去他们两个
I won't lose them both.
晦，我们能谈谈吗？
Hi .... Can we talk?
1央点，我有个会要开
Make it fast.  I've got a meeting.
10年来你一直在运营基希斯
The ten years you have been running GEN-SYS,
开发了多少药物
how many drugs have come down the pipeline that could save millions of lives?
可以拯救成千上万的生命
可以改变一切？
That could change everything?
你在说什么？
What are you talking about?
那个ALZ一112
The ALZ-112.
威尔，你怎么了？
What happened to you, Will?
你曾经是这个实验室的明星
You used to be the star of this lab. Now, you hardly ever show
现在你几乎不出现 而且当你现身时
你浪费时间 你的团队纠结在一种药上
and when you do, you waste your time and that of your team's
fixating on a drug
在那事儿发生之后 这种药绝对不会通过的
that, after what happened, is never ever going to get approved.
112太危险了，威尔 不会成功的
The 112 is dangerous, Will,
and it doesn't work.
我用它来治疗我父亲 有效的
I treated my father with it.
It does work.
你用了什么？你干了什么？
You did, what?
他打败了疾病，就像我们预言那样
You did, what!?
Beat the disease, like we predicted.
一带他进来 一有一个并发症
Brilliant.
There's been a complication.
恩，这有效的，不是么？
Well, does it work or doesn't it?
我父亲的病最后还是盖过了疗程
My father's disease eventually outran the cure.
我的老天
Oh, for goodness sake.
他的免疫系统创造了抗体 抵御了病毒成分
The immune system produced antibodies to beat the viral component,
但是一定会成功的
but it will work.
我已经开发了一种病毒变体 我想会更具攻击性
I've have already developed a virus strain
that I think will be more aggressive.
你这么认为么？
You think?
就让我测试一下吧
Just, let me test it.
你在浪费我的时间
You're wasting my time.
还有更多的
There's more!
这个应用超越了疾病本身
The applications go beyond the disease.
有迹象显示
There are indications that show the therapy can improve cognitive functioning,
疗程可以提高认知功能，记忆质量…
memory quality ...
What, what are you saying?
My father didn't just recover.
He improved.
You mean, increased intelligence?
It's not conclusive, but yes.
I want you, to start testing the revised 112 on chimps, A-S-A-P.
Okay.
I'll give you whatever you need, but get started.
Dinner time!
Great Ape, primate!
Go on, don't you know food when you see it?
你看到了不知道那是食物吗？
你觉得那好笑吗？
You think that's funny, huh?
我给你看看什么叫好笑
I show you something funny!
很快他就知道谁是老大了
You'll learn who's boss, soon enough.
一他的衣服怎么办？ 一什么怎么办？
What about his clothes?
我不知道
What about 'em?
I don't know ... May cause problems with the other apes.
会给其他猿类带来麻烦
好吧
Good!
寄送到： 基希斯
我数了10只猿类，对吗？
I counted ten apes, correct?
对
Yep.
好，一直到后面
Good.  All the way to the back.
好
你们都进展很快 为什么这么赶？
You guys are moving really quick on this. What's the big rush?
回想第一天，你还在抱怨
First day back, you're still complaining.
可巴，晦，我是威尔
Koba. Hi, I'm Will.
好，这个
This one.
他很安静
He's very calm.
对，这家伙去了很多实验室 见惯不惊了
Yeah.
He's been through a whole lot of labs. He knows the drill.
他知道训练流程
我想我可以加入你们
Could I join you, what's our progress.
看我们的进展
让他准备好
Get him prepped.
戴紧你的面具
Tighten your masks.
递给我113
Pass me the 113.
血氧指数不错，血压稳定
Pulse-ox is good, blood pressure is steady.
输送到位
Perisol delivery, in place.
释放113
Releasing the 113.
We have a break!
富兰克林，戴上你的面具！
Franklin, get your mask on!
一好了？ 一对
Got it?
拴紧皮带
Yeah.
你还好吗？
You okay?
恩，还好
Yeah, okay.
火箭
1央走！我们走吧！
Move it!  Let's go!
起来运动运动，你个懒骨头！
Get up and do some exercises you lazy baboons!
巴克
雅各布斯
智商结果令人惊讶 毫无倒退迹象
Intelligence results are remarkable.
There are no adverse effects.
猿类的免疫系统真是超级强大
Apes have amazingly strong immune systems.
对，好了，好好观察
All right, keep an eye on him.
好的
Okay. [Franklin sneezes]
关于那个很抱歉
Sorry about that.
这些家伙比我更灵活
These guys are more resiliant than I am.
抱歉等一下
Excuse me a second.
零下86度冰柜
伤得很重吗？
You seriously injured?
Do you know sign language?
你知道手语吗？
马戏团猩猩
I worked at the circus.
他很好
He's good.
小心点，人类和聪明的猿类可不同
Be Careful. Humans do not like intelligent apes.
寄送到：基希斯 “幸运”
我要你今晚工作到很晚
You're working late tonight.
基希斯还需要三份
GEN-SYS needs three more.
嘿，嘿嘿！
一嘿 一嘿，凯撒，你好
Hey, Caesar!
你受伤了吗？
Are you hurt?
给我看看
Show me.
凯撒，把手递给我
Caesar, give me your hand. Give me your hand.
把手递给我，没事的
有时候新来的孩子会被欺负
Sometimes, the new kid on the block gets picked on.
别担心 天啊，他们对你做了什么？
Stay calm. What did they do?
胡说，你到底做了什么？
That's bullshit!
一放手 一嘿！这儿有什么问题？
What's the problem here?
我要把他带出这里，现在
I'm taking him out of here, right now.
如果没有法定命令，你不可以
Not without a court order, you're not.
他不再是你的了
He's not yours, anymore.
我保证 如果我发现他被虐待，任何方式
I promise, if I find out he's been mistreated in any way,
我会让这鬼地方关门
I'll have this place shut down.
继续
Go on ...
嘿，你好
嘿
不
No.  No, we're not going home, right now.
不，现在我们不回家
I'm going to get you out of here, I promise.
但是我会带你离开这里 我保证
你得相信我
You have to trust me.
凯撒，你得相信我，好吗？
Caesar, you have to trust me, okay?
我想访问结束了
I think this visit's over.
相信我，会好的
Trust me.
You'll be okay.
来吧！走，我们走吧！
Come on, move it! Let's go!
哇！有上百只
There are hundreds of them! Looks like you're own private zoo!
这就像你自己的私人动物园
更像是这些毛毛家伙的监狱
Rather like a prison for hairy dudes.
他们看电视吗？
They watch TV?
我们称之为丰富生活
We call it enrichment.
这只太可爱了！
Aw, this one's so cute!
他叫什么名字？
What's his name?
名字是科纳利亚，是母的
Uh, name's Cornelia. It's a she.
[shreek]
一哦，我的天！ 一别靠太近
Oh, my God!
这只把我吓得半死
Don't get too close!
This one scared me half to death.
对，那个大家伙叫毛里斯
That big guy is called, Maurice.
不好玩
It's no fun.
来，我给你看看什么叫好玩
Here, I'll show you something fun.
看看这个
Check this out!
你疯了吗？
It's crazy!
你不应该来的
You shouldn't be in here.
嘿，你是下一个！
Hey, you're next!
来吧，我们走吧
Come on, let's go.
我在这儿花了很多时间
We spent too much time in here, as it is.
来吧
Come on!
看看这个家伙
Check out this guy.
嘿，那只真是个大麻烦
Hey, Alan, he's a pain in the ass. He thinks he's special, or something
他觉得他很特别
真奇怪
Freaky!
嘿，到这儿来
Hey, come here.
就像他在想什么似的…
I think he's thinking or something.
哦，我的天！他掐住了他的喉咙！
Oh, my God, he's got him by the throat!
一放开他！ 一放手！
Let him go!
Let go!
一你还好吗？ 一我还行
Are you okay?
我告诉你了别太靠近的
Yes.
I told you not to get too close, man.
来吧，伙计们，我们离开这里
Come on, guys, let's get out of here.
朱立斯凯撒
嘿
有些事情不该改变的
Some things aren't meant be changed.
你需要接受那个
You need to accept that.
嘿！
Hey!
嘿！这里发生什么了？
更多113的实验，我们刚准备了…
What's going on here?
不，我们得先分析可巴的血样
More 113 trials. We're just prepping ...
Oh, no, we have to analyze Koba's blood work first!
富兰克林知道这的，他在哪儿？
Franklin knows this. Where is he?
他请了两天病假
He's out sick for two days.
我没有同意这个
Well, I didn't authorized this.
不
No!
我同意了
I did.
我们同意就同一主体分开测试
We agreed to test sparingly on one subject.
那个主体真是让人惊奇
And, that one subject is stunning!
是一种病毒 我们不知道和人类相关的影响
It's a virus. We don't know the human related effects.
那种药很成功，威尔 告诉他，琳达
The drug works, Will.
一开始，可巴在卢卡斯塔游戏上 得了完美的15分
Tell him, Linda.
For starters, Koba scored a perfect 15 on the Lucas Tower.
每个测试结果都证实了其有效性
Every test result verifies its effectiveness.
一不要再测试了 一你是说…
No more tests. - What are you ...?
直到我们更清楚了解这个 我们不会再进一步测试
Not until we have a better understanding of what we're dealing with.
喂，我要告诉你我们正… 嘿，给我们一点时间
Look, I'll tell you exactly what we do. Look ...
抱歉，把猿放回笼子里 温柔点
Give us a minute.
Excuse me!   Put the ape back in the cage. Be gentle.
威尔，我要告诉你我们正在操作的事情
Will, I'll tell you exactly what we're dealing with, here.
我们搞的是一种药
We're dealing with a drug that is worth more
比我们开发的其他药加起来 的总和还要有价值
than everything else we are developing, combined.
你创造了历史，我挣了钱 那不是我们的安排么？
You make history,
I make money.
不，有风险
Isn't that our arrangement? - No! There are risks.
别和我谈什么风险不风险的
Don't you tell me about risks.
你给了你自己的父亲 一种尚在实验的药
You give your own father an experimental drug.
我只消一个电话 就可以毁掉你的职业生涯
I could finish your career with one phone call.
我会帮你省掉这麻烦的，我辞职
I'll save you the trouble. I quit.
没有你我们会照样继续的
We will proceed without you.
你不知道你在做什么
Look ... You do not know what you're doing.
这些测试需要小规模监管
These tests need to be contained.
你根本不知道113是否稳定 它对人们可能造成什么样的伤害
You have no idea if the 113 is stable,
what kind of damage it can do to people ...
是的，这就是为什么 我们在黑猩猩身上做实验
Well, that is why we test it on chimps, ... isn't it?
不是么？
罗德曼博士，是我，富兰克林！ 我需要和你谈谈！
Dr. Rodman, it's, me, Franklin! I need to talk to you!
你可以到门前来吗？
Can you come to the door?
博士？
Doc! [coughing]
你是谁啊？
Who the hell are you? [Franklin sneezes on neighbor]
给我滚！
Get out of here!
抱歉，抱歉
I'm sorry, ... I'm sorry.
你不会要陷害我吧？
You wouldn't be trying to entrap me, would you?
呢，我不能说我同意
Well, ... I can't say that I approve.
他们不是人类，你知道
They're not people, you know.
你会让他走还是不让？
You gonna to let him go or not?
凯撒？嘿，过来
Caesar, ... hey, come on.
来吧，我们回家
Come on, we're go home.
回家
Home.
来，我们真的回去了
Come on, we're really going.
来吧，我们离开这里
Let's get out of here.
对
Yeah ... Come on.
来
凯撒？
Caesar?
我想他更喜欢这里，和他的同类一起
I guess he likes it better here with his own kind.
为什么饼干火箭？
Why cookies, Rocket?
猿类孤独…
A single monkey ... is weak.
马写
猿类一起强壮
Monkeys together - a force
猿类很傻
Monkeys are stupid.
该死的，罗德尼！ 你又把水枪放在中庭外了？
Damn it, Rodney,
什么？不！
You leave the hose out in the atrium, again?
What?   No!
1央点！我们走！
Come on!  Let's go.
1央，起来！
Come on, Get up!
惊人新闻 伊卡洛斯进入了火星大气
[On TV] Eight months after its launch,
在发射8月之后 地球的首次载人太空飞行到火星…
Earth's first manned space flight to Mars ...
我发誓，道奇，我讲的都是实话
I ain't dodging. I'm telling the truth.
对，呢，如果你没拿我的饼干 那究竟是谁拿的？
Yeah, well, if I've didn't take the cookies,
一我不知道 一嘿！
Then, who the hell did?
你们俩大傻瓜可以停一下吗？
I, I do not know ...
Hey!  Will you two morons knock it off!
我要回家了
I'm going home.
[On TV] ... covered in water and therefore able to sustain life.
我在他妈猿类房里感觉更安静
I get more peace in the God-damned ape house.
爸爸，抱歉
Dad, I'm sorry!
一做得好，罗德尼 一我发誓…
富兰克林先生？是多蒂
Mr. Franklin, it's Dottie!
富兰克林先生？
Mr. Franklin? ... Hello?
喂？
他妈的发生了什么？
What the hell?
神说：“让水带来 移动的物种…
罗德尼，现在到平台来
[Over radio] Rodney, get to the platform, now.
罗德尼！
[Over radio] Rodney!
你以为你他妈的在做什么？
What the hell do you think you're doing, huh?
走！
Get!
继续，回到你的笼子里
Go on!
我警告你
Get back in your cage!
I'm warning you!
继续，走！
Go on, get!
就这样
That's it!
看到了么？那就是你所得的！ 现在回来！
That's what you get! ... Get back!
你是怎么了？
What's wrong with you?
傻猴子！
Dumb monkey!
把你的臭爪子从我身上拿开！ 你他妈的脏猿猴！
Take your stinking paw off me, you damn dirty ape!
不！
No!
不！不！不！
不！不！
No!
不！
我发誓我要把你们每一个的皮扒掉！
I'll beat all!
基希斯
卡罗琳，你去过凯撒的房间吗？
Caroline, have you been up to Caesar's room?
没人答话
No one's answering.
兰登？
Landon!
基希斯
威尔？
Will!
威尔！
发生什么了？
What happened?
他说话了
He spoke.
你什么…什么？
What are you ... what?
你的猿
Your ape ... he spoke.
他说话了
旧金山编年史 太空迷失？
他妈发生什么了？
What in the hell?
我不敢相信
I don't believe this.
…我要把你们每一个的皮扒掉！
[Video] I'll beat each and everyone of you.
我需要人手来和旧金山警局配合 告诉他们我们有难
I need someone to coordinate with the S.F.P.D.
一是什么？ 一我知道他前去的方向
Tell them we got a fatality.
What is it?
I know where he's headed.
楞？
Glenn?
我们走吧
Let's go!
一雅各布斯 一雅各布斯先生，我是威尔团队里的琳达
Jacobs.
[Cell phone] Mr. Jacobs, It's Linda from Will's team.
发生了很糟糕的事情
Look, something terrible has happened.
富兰克林死了，感染了病毒
Franklin is dead from a viral infection.
你在说什么？
What the hell are you talking about?
他被染上了113
He was exposed to the 113. It does something
这个对猿类无害 但是对人类有害
to people that it doesn't do to apes.
他将不得不通过城市 跨过大桥
We'll have to go through the city and across the bridge.
雅各布斯先生？雅各布斯先生，你是否…
[Cell phone] Mr. Jacobs? Mr. Jacobs, are you ...
发生什么了？
What the hell?
史蒂芬雅各布斯！
I am Steven Jacobs!
这是我的实验室，我们刚被破坏了
It's full of apes in there. I gotta get in the air!
我们需要广播通告
We have to be able to destroy them.
追踪他们并抓住他们！好吗？
等一下！等一下
Just, trust me on this! Okay?
瞧，这事儿你得相信我！好吗？
你们最好把相机备好
You might want to get your cameras ready.  Normally,
一般这些家伙非常害羞
these guys are quit shy.
他们一般会在公园北面穿行
They're going  the park, on the north side!
一他们有领导！ 一按下按钮！
Find the lead!
一什么？ 一按钮！
You gotta hold the button! The button!
他们有领导！ 这些猿类比你想象得更聪明！
They're being led.  These apes are smarter than you think.
我们得干掉领导！
They've got a leader!
不，你别告诉他们我被困在堵车中了
Do not tell them I am stuck in traffic. Make up with something smarter!
你想点聪明的借口吧！等下
Hold on.
他妈的…
What the ...
他们在桥上
They're on the bridge.
他们试着去红木林
They're trying to get to the redwoods.
旧金山警局一号队，这是空军
SFPD, Police 1.
This is Air Ops,
封锁南边出口 马奇行队状态如何？
[On radio] Seal of south end. What's the status of those units?
准装待发，长官
[Radio response] Ready to go, sir.
好的 一旦他们赶上你，就往北冲！
[On radio] As soon as they reach you, block them.
北面 我们会把他们向你们推进
[On Radio] North side, we're going to push them right to you.
没问题，我们准备好了
[Radio response] No problem. We're ready for them.
北面封锁了
The north side is blocked. [On radio] They'll never get through here.
他们绝对通不过这里
一旦他们到了界限 我们就拿下他们！
As soon as they hit the gap, we'll take them out!
一你要射击他们？ 一就像往桶里射鱼
You can just shoot them? Like shooting fish in a barrel.
好
Good!
转弯，继续前进 下桥，先生
Turn that thing around!
一不，你不了解 一你才不了解！
Get off the bridge, sir. I can't ...
现在给我下桥！ 这是疏散，出来！
You don't understand. Get off this bridge, now!
一所有市民清空 一请确认
This is an evacuation.  Get out!
All the civilians, clear.
让这些人下桥！
[On radio] Please confirm.
Put these people off the bridge!
等下！
上去
下去
预备派送骑行队
Stand by, city mounted units!
他们会杀掉他们的
They're gonna slaughter them.
一我要去救凯撒 一嘿，嘿，嘿
I'm gonna to get Caesar.
Will, hey!
听着
你小心点
You, be careful!
嘿！
从那儿下来 那）L你不能去的
I gotta get to my car!
但是我得去开我的车！放开我！
Get out of here!
我得去开我的车，那很重要！
Let go me!  I have to get my car!
嘿！
把他们往北赶！
Push 'em north!
让路啊！
Get out of the way!
不！
快点，不然你在雾里就把他们跟丢了！
{On radio] Hurry, we're going to lose them in the fog.
就那么做！
Do It!
他们在哪儿？我看不到他们
Where are they?  I don't see them!
CHp北部，你能看到什么吗？
[On radio] CHP North, do you have a visual?
不能，先生，什么都看不到
No, sir, negative.
安全阀拉下！
Safety's off!
停火！停火！
Hold your fire!
撤退！撤退！大家都撤退！
Back!
凯撒！
Caesar!
就是他，那是领导
That's him!   That's the leader!
255，进来！你在吗？
[On radio] They're in sight! Put 'em down!
帮帮我
Help me!
抓住我的手
Take my hand!
来吧，来吧
Come, come on ...
来吧
Come on!
不
来吧
不是你
Not you ...
不！不！
No!
傻猴子！
Save me!
不！不！
凯撒！
Caesar!
凯撒？
Caesar?
凯撒
Caesar ... I'm sorry.
抱歉，这是我的错
This is my fault.
这必须停止，不该这样
This has to stop.
This isn't the way.
你知道他们的能耐
You know what they're capable of.
请回家吧
Please come home.
如果你回家，我会保护你的
If you come home, I'll protect you.
凯撒已经在家了
Caesar is home.
好吧
Okay.
凯撒已经在家了
Caesar's home.
走吧
Go.
Subtitles by dhyco
一个未知的群体 制造了一个大型的骚乱
就在这里，旧金山海湾
包括城市动物园和金门大桥
造成了大面积的损失 也有一些人受伤
目击者也报告说 看到猿类穿过城市
Mandar 1 n 5 1 mp 1 1 f 1 ed